<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine briefe questions and answers, concerning chiefe poynts of Christian religion Gathered for the vse of the young people of the parish of S. Andrewes in Eastcheape: and may serue generally for all places. By N.A.</title>
            <author>Allsopp, Nicholas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 382.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116751</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 304:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine briefe questions and answers, concerning chiefe poynts of Christian religion Gathered for the vse of the young people of the parish of S. Andrewes in Eastcheape: and may serue generally for all places. By N.A.</title>
                  <author>Allsopp, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Jones] for T. P[avier.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>N.A. = Nicholas Allsopp.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 10.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10 on UMI microfilm reel 304.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology --  Miscellanea --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:1"/>
            <p>CERTAINE. Briefe Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Anſwers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning chiefe poynts of Chriſtian religion Gathered for the vſe of the young people of the pariſh of S. <hi>Andrewes</hi> in Eaſtcheape: and may ſerue generally for all places. By N. A.</p>
            <p>At London printed for T. P.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:2"/>
            <head>CERTAINE Briefe Queſtions and Anſwers, concerning chiefe poyntes of Chriſtian Religion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVHo created you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> GOD the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who redeemed you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who ſanctified you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherefore did he create the world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For his owne glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherefore did he create man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſerue him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. In what doe we ſerue God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In <hi>5.</hi> things:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> In praying to him,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Prayſing him.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Hearing his word.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> Vſing his Sacraments</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> Keeping his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which are his Commaundements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe ten which God gaue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Are there but ten Commaundements for vs to keepe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No more, for all other Commaundements, either in the old Teſtament, or in the new, doe in their ſubſtance belong to ſome of theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the ſumme or drift of theſe Commaundements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſumme of the firſt foure, is to loue God aboue all. And the ſumme of the laſt ſixe, is to loue our neighbour as our ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who is our neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not onely our friendes and acquaintance, but euen ſtrangers, and enemies; and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſtandes in neede of mercie: As Chriſt ſheweth by the example of the wounded man</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Are you, or any man, able to keepe this law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, wée are not able.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How know you that you are not able?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> My Conſcience doth accuſe mee of my ſinnes. <hi>2.</hi> The Scripture hath teſtified that all haue offended, &amp; haue neede of Gods grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is the law then vnpoſſible to be kept?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How is God righteous, to giue a law vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> Becauſe it was not vnpoſſible to <hi>Adam</hi> in his firſt eſtate. <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe God of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie prouided that the vnpoſſible righteouſneſſe of the Law, ſhould be fulfilled in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How comes it then to paſſe, that wee are not able to keepe this Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe wee all doe from our Parents in our very conception, draw corruption, that makes vs vnable to kéepe the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is this corruption of nature in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> Blindneſſe in our vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Crookedneſſe in our heartes, to know good and euill.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Not to deſire good, and hate euill.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Peruerſeneſſe in our imagination and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, to remember and thinke of good thinges badly and of euill and vaine thinges eaſily, and with delight. <hi>Gen. <hi>6.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the puniſhment, of the breach of the Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Laboure and miſery in our bodyes, and death and euerlaſting damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What meanes is there to be deliuered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What was Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond perſon in Trinitie: God and man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why was he man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That he might ſuffer ſuch puniſhment as was due to man,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why was he God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That he might ouercome it, and that the puniſhment might be a ſufficient price; which could not bée, but by ſuch a perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How did he redeeme vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By bearing the puniſhment of our ſinnes, dying vpon the Croſſe, and by performing a perfect righteouſnes for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How are theſe to be accepted for vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they were not needfull, for Chriſt himſelfe who neuer deſerued any puniſhment, becauſe hee was without ſinne nor was bound to performe any Law, being God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How ſhall wee be pertakers of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In feeling and grieuing for our ſinnes, wee beleeue that Chriſt dyed for our ſinnes, and roſe for our Iuſtification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How ſhall we come to haue a feeling of our Sinn?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A,</hi> By looking into the Commaundementes. By examining our liues. By conſidering Gods bleſſings and iudgementes,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How ſhall we come to Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith is the guift of GOD: but wrought in vs by the Word, Sacramentes,
<pb facs="tcp:17263:4"/> and Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q, How doth the Word beget Fayth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Precepts doe let vs ſee the number of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>The Iudgement doth make vs feele them heauie, and ſo to ſeeke for eaſe</p>
            <p>The Promiſes make vs to hope: and ſo both Precepts and Threatnings; or Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Promiſes, make vs to beget Fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How do the Sacraments beget Fayth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As Seales do ſerue to confirme Writings: and tokens, and pledges, betweene men and men, do confirme promiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A,</hi> Two and no more: Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How can the taking of a little Water or Wine, ſeale vp my Fayth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God is ſo true and powerfull, and whatſoeuer ſigne he giues, it is an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, bee the meanes neuer ſo ſimple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What be the outward thinges to be ſeene in Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Water: which ſignifieth the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What thinges are done in Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Dipping into the Water, Waſhing, and
<pb facs="tcp:17263:5"/> riſing out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What do theſe ſignifie &amp; declare vnto me</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The waſhing, doth betoken the waſhing of my ſinnes, the putting into the Water, repreſentes a buriall, as it were into Chriſtes death to die to ſinne: and the riſing out doth ſignifie my ingraffing into Chriſtes reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to riſe to newneſſe of life, as he did riſe from death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the outward thinges in the Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are rhe viſible things done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Receiuing, and eating.</p>
            <p>Breaking the Bread.</p>
            <p>Diſtributing both to the people,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doe theſe ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> the firſt ſignifieth Chriſts paſſion.</p>
            <p>The diſtributing ſignifieth that it was done, that others [not himſelfe] might haue the benefite.</p>
            <p>The receiuing and eating, betokens and aſſures that euery one that receiues, is knit to the body and bloud of Chriſt, as he doth vnite the Bread and Wine to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What comfort haue we by this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I am aſſured that all the vertue of the Bread and Wine being receiued, becomes
<pb facs="tcp:17263:5"/> mine: and ſo being ſpiritually, by fayth, ioyned to Chriſt, I ſhall be made partaker of all the benefites of his death and reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. ſhall euery one that commeth to this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, haue this comfort?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> None but they that come worthily: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they eate their owne damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Can any come worthily to it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not as deſeruing to come: but by faith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, through the merrit and worthines of Ieſus Chriſt imputed and applied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How ſhall we come to it worthily?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By meanes. Firſt to come, to it, as a Supper made by GOD, of great price and delight. Secondly as vnto a Supper where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is preſented the bitter death of Chriſt the Sonne of GOD, and our vniting to him, as to our head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What affections doe become it, as it is Gods Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, thankefulneſſe to him that hath prepared ſo great a Supper &amp; called vs vnto it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a hunger and thirſting after the meate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, an humilitie in heart in regard of our vnworthineſſe, to take the loweſt place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What affections become it, as there is a
<pb facs="tcp:17263:6"/> repreſentation of Chriſtes death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Foure.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Sorrow for ſinne.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Perſwaſion of forgiuenes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> A purpoſe of a holy life.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> Loue and charitie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thus beeing furniſhed, wee ſhall come (as Chriſtians) to receiue fully Chriſtes bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites: GOD which graunt we may.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:6"/>
            <head>¶ A Prayer, wherein is conteyned the ſubſtance of all the Catechiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt mightie God merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and louing Father, who haſt giuen vs our life in this world for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that our greateſt care aboue all other thinges might be, that our moſt pretious ſoules might be ſaued for euer in the day of Iudgement and for the ſame end haſt appointed the miniſtrie and preaching of the word, as the onely powerfull meanes to bring vs to thy euerlaſting kingdome of glory: we beſeech thée for thine owne name ſake, and for Ieſus Chriſt thy déere Sonnes ſake, giue vs grace with humble &amp; carefull hearts to learne and knowe ſo much out of thy bleſſed and holy word, as may be for the ſaluation of our ſoules from hell and condemnation, and to bring vs to the ioy of thy kingdome. Graunt that now in time we may from the true vnderſtanding of thy bleſſed Lawe, both ſée &amp; féele the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all our ſinnes, and of that puniſhment which we haue deſerued therefore, that wée
<pb facs="tcp:17263:7"/> being loden with the heauie burden of our ſinnes, may with broken and ſad hearts ſeeke for eaſe and helpe now in this time of our life, while eaſe and helpe may be obteined: for after this life there is no mercy, but iudgement and vengeance to be looked for. And when as by thy ſpirit thou haſt caſt vs downe with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned repentance, and hartie ſorrow for all our ſinnes paſt either knowne or vnknown vnto vs: then wee pray thee comfort and lift vp our poore diſtreſſed conſciences, with the ſtrength of a liuely faith grounded vpon thy promiſe made vnto vs in the Goſpell, which may in Chriſt his death perſwade our heartes of the full pardon of all our ſinnes, and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of that puniſhment which we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued with good aſſurance in his perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, wrought in our nature, in his owne perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs, to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inheritance of euerlaſting life, in thy moſt bleſſed kingdome. And wee hartely beſeech thee, that this faith of ours may be fruitfull in euery part of our inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward behauiour to our owne comfort, and the good example of all other, among whome we ſhall haue our conuerſation. Graunt further, that this faith may dayly be vnderpropped and vpholden againſt all the violent aſſaultes of Sathan, and doubting weakenes of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb facs="tcp:17263:7"/> nature, by thoſe plaine pledges and loue tokens (I meane the Sacraments) which thou haſt mercifully prouided to put vs out of doubt of thine euerlaſting loue toward vs in Ieſus Chriſt. Laſtly that we may from time to time, from day to day, and from houre in houre, haue good experience, and true triall of thy good will; giue vs grace with vpright harts to call vpon thée in the name of thy Sonne our aloone Sauiour for all good graces and bleſſings needfull for our ſoules and bodies for this life preſent, and for the life to come, both for our ſelues, and for all the Church and children, that thus wée may glorifie thée ſo long as wee ſhall liue heere vpon the face of the earth, and may heereafter be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of euerlaſting glory in thy kingdome, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Grace before meat.</head>
            <p>MOſt gratious Father, who féedeſt all creatures which depend vpon thy diuine prouidence, wee beſeech thée ſanctifie theſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which thou haſt ordained to vs, giue them vertue to nouriſh our bodies, in life and health, &amp; giue vs grace to receiue them ſoberly and thankefully as from thy handes: that ſoe
<pb facs="tcp:17263:8"/> in the ſtrength of theſe, and other thy bleſſings we may walke in the vprightnes of our hearts, before thy face, this day and all the dayes of our liues, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and only Sauiour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Or thus.</head>
            <p>Moſt gratious God &amp; mercifull Father, we beſeech thée ſanctifie thy creatures to our vſe, make them healthfull for our nurriſhment, and vs thankefull for all thy bleſſings, through Chriſt our Lord and onely Sauiour: Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Grace after meate.</head>
            <p>Bleſſed be thy holy name O Lord our God for theſe thy good benefits, wherewith thou haſt ſoe plentifully at this time refreſhed our bodies, O Lord vouchſafe likewiſe to féede our ſoules, with the ſpirituall foode of thy holy word and ſpirit vnto life euerlaſting: O Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and ſaue thy whole Church, our gratious King and Quéene, our noble Prince the Duke of Yoarke, and Lady <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> forgiue vs our ſinnes and vnthankefullnes, paſſe by our manifold infermities, make vs all mindefull of our liues ends, and of the reckonings we are to mke to thée therein, and in the meane time
<pb facs="tcp:17263:8"/> graunt vnto vs health, peace and truth, in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord &amp; onely Sauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Or thus.</head>
            <p>Bleſſed be thy holy name O Lord for theſe thy good benefits wherewith thou haſt refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs at this time: Lord forgiue vs all our ſinnes and frailetyes, ſaue thy Church, King and Quéene, and royall proſterity, and graunt vs health, peace and truth, in Chriſt our onely Sauiour Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Before meate.</head>
            <p>Sanctifie vnto vs O Lord the vſe of theſe thy creatures, of which by our ſinnes we haue made our ſelues vnworthy, make vs ſober and thankefull receiuers of them, graunt that the end of our eatings and drinkings, may be to be better inabled to ſerue thée in our ſeuerall places, through Ieſus Chriſt Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Another.</head>
            <p>Take from vs O gratious Father all gloto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and exceſſe, all carnall féeding without feare, all minding of none but earthly things, all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing our bellies without prouiding for our
<pb facs="tcp:17263:9"/> ſoules, make vs mindefull of thy preſence, and carefull for to behaue our ſelues in receiuing theſe creatures ſet before vs, that all that wee doe, may be to thy glory, and to the comfort of our ſoules, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Another grace.</head>
            <p>Humble our ſoules before thée O Lord, and cauſe vs to ſee the ſmalnes of our deſert euen in reſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt of thy mercies: make vs to hunger after Chriſt by whom only the free vſe of thy creatures is reſtored to vs: &amp; giue vs ſo to enioy theſe bleſſings heare prouided for vs, with that reuerence and ſobriety as in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, that our bodyes being refreſhed our ſoules may praiſe thee who art the giuer of all good, and that in Ieſus Chriſt the righteous. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Another.</head>
            <p>O Lord, it is not bread that we liue by, but by the word that proceeded from thy mouth, lift vp our hearts to looke vnto thee for a bleſſing vppon our meates, and vouchſafe vs the gratious aſſurance of thy loue in Chriſt, that we may comfortably vſe thy creatures as pledges of thy fauour, &amp; be prouoked by them
<pb facs="tcp:17263:9"/> to giue vp our ſelues to thy glory, to ſerue thee inſinceryty all our daies, through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Another Grace before meate.</head>
            <p>Teach vs to remember O mercifull God, that it is thou, which to vs and all thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures giueſt foode in due ſeaſon, that ſoe wée may take héede of all vnthankfull and brutiſh vſing of theſe good things, which in thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thou haſt ordayned for vs: raiſe vp our affections to longe for thy foode which indureth to eternall life, which Ieſus hath promiſed to giue vs, who is thy onely ſonne and our onely ſauiour Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Another Grace after meate.</head>
            <p>Wée magnifie thy name O Lord for all thy mercies, for the comfortable refreſhings which thou haſt now vouchſafed vs: pardon we beſeech thée our great vnthankefullnes, in the duties of obedience to thy bleſſed will: ſaue all thy Church, protect and bleſſe our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious King, and his Realmes, the Quéene, the Prince, and all their royall progeny, graunt paſſage to thy Goſpell, comfort to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and peace of conſcience to vs all in Ieſus Chriſt: Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:10"/>
            <head>Another Grace after meate.</head>
            <p>As thou haſt filled our bodyes, O Lord, with thy good creatures, farre aboue our beſt deſeruing, ſo be pleaſed, we pray thee, to ſeaſon our ſoules, and to endue vs with all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſſings in heauenly things, that in all our life, that yet remaynes, we may be meanes of glory to thy Name, of credit to thy Goſpell, and of much comfort to thy ſeruants: preſerue thy Church, protect this whole State, and the Chiefe-head thereof, King <hi>Iames,</hi> his Quéene, his Heyre, and whole poſterity, the Counſell, the Nobles, the Maieſtrates, the Miniſters of thy word, comfort the hearts of all thy ſeruants, ſtabliſh vs all in thy truth, and keepe vs for euer to thy ſelfe, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Grace before meate.</head>
            <p>Bleſſed be thou, O Lord, for theſe, and for all thy gifts: let thy mercy to our bodyes ſtirre vp thankefulnes in our ſoules, and let our care to pleaſe thee in our liues, bee a witnes of the feeling we haue of thy rich and abundant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies towards vs: be gracious to all thy people through the world, forget not theſe Realmes,
<pb facs="tcp:17263:10"/> nor thine annoynted, our Soueraigne King, the Queene, the hopefull Prince, and the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Progeny: diſapoynt the enemies of thy Goſpell, and make it to grow in deſpight of Sathan, to the glory of thy Name, and to the reioycing of the ſoules of all thy ſeruants, for Ieſus ſake, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Another Grace before meate.</head>
            <p>Accept, we pray thée, (moſt louing Father) this our ſacrifice of prayſe, which for theſe, and all thy fauours, we here offer vp vnto thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, looke vpon it in the worthyneſſe of thy Sonne, and for his ſake enable vs to a chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruing thee in ſinglenes of heart, and in vprightneſſe of conuerſation all our dayes: and looke mercyfully vpon the whole body of thine elect, liuing vpon this earth whereſoeuer, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply thy mercyes vpon the ſeuerall Churches vnited vnder the gouernment of our gracious King, powre out thy graces vpon him and his, continue the truth of Religion to vs and our poſterity, enlarge the Kingdome of grace, and haſten the Kingdome of glory, and preſerue vs by thy power thereunto, through Ieſus Chriſt our onely Sauiour, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:11"/>
            <head>Grace after meate.</head>
            <p>Wee returne vnto thee, with the humbling of our hearts, all poſſible thanks O gratious God for thy loue and bountie towards vs thy vnworthy ſeruants, for electing vs for ſending thy ſonne to die for vs, for calling vs to a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope by thy precious Goſpell, for creating, for preſeruing, for feeding vs at this preſent: O ſtirre vs vp to giue our ſelues vnto thee, and to conſecrate our whole ſpirits, ſoules and bodies to thy glory all our dayes.</p>
            <p>O Lord, ſaue thy Church, our King, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer before meate.</head>
            <p>GRatious God, and mercifull Father, we pray thee for Ieſus Chriſts ſake to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs the ſinnes of all our life paſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and together with the full forgiuenes thereof, bleſſe theſe good creatures ſet before vs at this time, that they may feede our bodies: and bleſſe vs with grace ſo to receiue them before thee with reuerence that wee may be the better able to goe forward w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our buſineſſe in our calling to thy glory, and our euerlaſting comfort in our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:11"/>
            <head>A Thankſgiuing after meate.</head>
            <p>WE thanke thee moſt mercifull Father, for the good comfort and ſtrength which thou haſt giuen vs at this time, by theſe thy good bleſſings of meat and drinke: we pray thée in like manner, comfort our poore ſoules with the euerlaſting foode of thy word preached vnto vs, that by the working of thy bleſſed ſpirit, we may practiſe it in the whole courſe of our life, to thy glory, and our ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt our onely Lord and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>An other Prayer before meate.</head>
            <p>MOſt louing and mercifull Father, who haſt giuen vs our life and breath, with all good bleſſings, for our ſoules and bodies, graunt thy good bleſſings to theſe meates and drinks now ſet before vs, that from thee, they may receiue ſtrength to feede vs, and giue vs ſuch grace to receiue and vſe them, that wee may be the better able with comfort of heart to ſerue thee ſo in this life that we may haue the comfort of thy kingdome, there to liue for euer, by Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:12"/>
            <head>An other Thankſgiuing after meat.</head>
            <p>WE confeſſe our ſelues for euer bound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee moſt mercifull Father, for all good bleſſings, and namely for theſe which now we haue ſo bountifully receiued to our great comfort mercifully pardon wee pray thee all our profanenes and vnthankefulnes paſt and preſent, and ſtrengthen vs for euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after with greater grace to ſhew our ſelues more thankefull vnto thee, and more carefull to ſerue thee in all true holines and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes all the dayes of our life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>An other Prayer before meate.</head>
            <p>HOly Father. we, confeſſe our ſelues moſt vnworthy of our life, or any other bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which may do vs good in ſoule or body, by reaſon of our ſinnes, which are both great and greeuous: we pray thee therefore in Chriſt his death forgiue them all, and in his obedience ſo receiue vs to fauour, as that for his ſake theſe good bleſſings may be bleſſed to our good vſe, to féede vs in our bodies, and to further vs in all godlines towards heauen &amp; euerlaſting life,
<pb facs="tcp:17263:12"/> through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>An other Thankſgiuing.</head>
            <p>WE confeſſe thy great goodnes towards vs moſt louing Father, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all our ſinnes, thou haſt fed vs at this time more plentifully then many thouſands of our brethren, who are more thankefull for any bleſſings receiued, and a thouſand times more carefull to ſerue thée then we be wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thée call vs not to account for that which is paſt but ſtrengthen vs with a rich portion of thy grace to bind our ſelues for euer heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to our better behauiour, to ſerue thee with better thankefulnes, and more carefull obedience all the daies of our life, to thy glory, and our euerlaſting comfort in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>Good Lord bleſſe the Church, preſerue our Kinges maieſty defend this whole land, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the comfortles, giue good ſucceſſe to thy Goſpell againſt all the foes of thy truth, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giue vs our ſinnes in Chriſt Ieſus, increaſe our faith, graunt peace to this Church and common wealth, and to euery one of vs in our conſcience, we moſt humbly entreate thee good Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:13"/>
            <head>A Thankes giuing before dinner.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Heauenly Father, which art the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and full treaſure of all goodnes, we beſeech thee to ſhew thy mercies vpon vs thy Children, and ſanctifie theſe gifts, which wee receiue of thy mercifull liberalitie, graunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs grace to vſe them ſoberly, and purely according to thy bleſſed will: ſo that thereby we may acknowledge thee to bee the Authour and giuer of all good things, and aboue all that wee may remember continually to ſeeke the ſpirituall foode of thy word, wherewith our ſoules may be nouriſhed euerlaſtingly through our Sauiour Chriſt who is the true bread of life which came downe from heauen, of whom, whoſoeuer eateth ſhall liue for euer. So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Thankes after Dinner.</head>
            <p>GLorie, praiſe and honour be vnto thee moſt mercifull, and omnipotent Father, who of thine infinit goodnes haſt created man to thine owne Image and ſimiltude, who alſo haſt fed, and dayly feedeſt of thy moſt bountifull hand all liuing creatures, graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that as thou haſt nouriſhed theſe our mortall bodies with corporall foode, ſo thou
<pb facs="tcp:17263:13"/> wouldeſt repleniſh our ſoules with the perfect knowledge of the liuely word of thy beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, to whom bee praiſe, glory, and honor for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <p>God ſaue the Church vniuerſall: GOD comfort them that be comfortleſſe: Lorde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our faith: O Lord for Chriſt thy ſons ſake, be mercifull to all the Common wealthes where thy Goſpell is truely preached, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour graunted to the afflicted members of Chriſtes body: and illuminate according to thy good pleaſure, all nations, with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy word, So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Thankeſgiuing after Supper.</head>
            <p>ETernall and euerlaſting God Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who of thy moſt ſingular loue, which thou beareſt to menkind, &amp; haſt appointed to his ſuſtenance, not only the fruites of the earth, but alſo the Foules of the ayre, and Beaſts, of the earth, and Fiſhes of the Sea, and haſt commanded thy benefites to bee receiued, as from thine hande, with thankeſgiuing, aſſuring thy children, by the mouth of thine Appoſtle, that to the cleane, all things are cleane, as the creatures which bee ſanctified by thy word, and by prayer: graunt
<pb facs="tcp:17263:14"/> vnto vs ſo moderately to vſe theſe thy giftes preſent, that the bodies being refreſhed, the ſoules may be more able to procéede in all good workes, to the praiſe of thy holy name, So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Thankeſgiuing after ſupper.</head>
            <p>THe GOD of all power, who hath called from death, the great Paſtor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhéepe, our Lord Ieſus, comfort and defend the flock, which he hath redeemed by the bloud of the eternall Teſtament: increaſe the number of true preachers: repreſſe the rage of obſtinate tyrants: mitigate, and lighten the heartes of the ignorant: relieue the paine of ſuch as bée afflicted: but eſpecially of thoſe that ſuffer for the teſtimonie of his trueth, and finally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Sathan, by the power of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer before the hearing or reading of the word, or any other exerciſe thereof</head>
            <p>BLeſſed Lord God moſt mercifull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, for as much as thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:17263:14"/> very ſtraightly charged vs in thy holy word, before all other things in this world, moſt chiefely and carefully to ſéeke thy kingdome and the righteouſnes thereof, where onely is true happines, which will laſt for euer: Graunt vs grace that the care and loue of this world, (whereto our earthly minds are too much wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) being ſet aſide, we may hencefoorth moſt diligently ſtudy how to liue for euer in thy bleſſed kingdome. And becauſe we haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from thine owne wiſdome, that the ſincere preaching of thy word is the playne path and beaten hye way which leadeth to the ioy of thy kingdome: we beſeech thée giue vs grace at all times, and vpon all occaſions, withall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and readineſſe of heart, to heare, reade, muſe, and ſtudy thereon, that our ſoules may dayly grow rich and wealthy in the increaſe of true repentance, faith, holines of life, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, patience, loue, and euery other ſweet fruit, of thy holy ſpirit, which may prepare vs to bee alwayes ready when it ſhall pleaſe thee to call vs out of this life, to liue moſt bleſſedly with thee for euer in thine euerlaſting Kingdome, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:15"/>
            <head>¶ A Thankeſgiuing after any exerciſe. <hi>of the Word of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVE thanke thee moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, for all good bleſſings what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, confeſſing our ſelues altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of any one of them from the firſt vnto the laſt, and from the greateſt vnto the ſmalleſt: moſt chiefly we thanke thee for the great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and pretious iewell of thy holy Word, and for the ſweete comfort thou bringeſt to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences by the continuall hearing, reading, ſtudy, &amp; excerciſe thereof. we pray the encreaſe our zeale and loue therevnto euery day more and more, that the power thereof may fo worke in euery one of our ſoules, that we may dayly proſper and thriue in all the wayes of Godlines to thy glory, and our euerlaſting comfort in thy kingdome, by Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer for the Euening.</head>
            <p>BLeſſe Lord God, moſt mercifull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, all we thy ſeruants whome thou haſt ioyned together in this houſhold, do altogether confeſſe thy maruellous great
<pb facs="tcp:17263:15"/> mercy which thou haſt ſhewed to euery one of vs all the dayes of our life, and by name, this day, which now is at an end, Wee all thanke thee from the very ground and bottome of our heartes, that thou haſt preſerued vs from all the dangers of our bodies, and from euery iudgement of our ſoules. We thanke thée that euery way thou haſt dealt ſo kindly and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with vs, ſhewing thy ſelfe a moſt tender father, as well in the bleſſings, of this preſent life, as alſo in the moſt excellent graces of a farre better life. Thou haſt prouided for vs (according to our calling) whatſoeuer thou in wiſedome knoweſt needfull for our bodely maintenance. As for our ſoules, thy loue hath appeared moſt wonderfull, becauſe thou haſt not ſuffered vs to runne headlong to hell in blindnes &amp; ignorance, with many thouſands, [whom thou haſt in thy fearefull, yet moſt iuſt iudgement, appointed vnto condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) but haſt by the bleſſed preaching of thy word which thou haſt brought among'ſt vs, ſhewed vs the way how to eſcape euerlaſting vengeance, and to liue for euer in thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. To this purpoſe thou haſt prolonged euery one of our liues vnto this preſent houre, and this day bleſſed vs with health &amp; ſtrength of our bodies to walke in our calling ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:17263:16"/> we haue with good ſucceſſe happely ended the buſines of this day, and therefore now this night we may betake our ſelues to comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table reſt, whereby we may w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> better courage and ſtrength returne againe to our buſines the next day following. For theſe and all other mercies whatſoeuer we moſt humbly thanke thée, praying thée moſt humbly to forgiue and forget the ſinnes of this day, and of all our life paſt, howſoeuer we haue committed them by thought, word, or déede, wittingly or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly through ignorance, or for want of good héed. Giue vs the ſight and ſorrow of heart for them all, with a full purpoſe for euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be more watchfull ouer all our wayes &amp; more héedefull in all our behauiour, then euer héeretofore wee haue béene. To this end, vouchſafe vpon vs a rich portion of thy grace ſo to profit by the hearing of thy word preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that we may more carefully auoyde that which is euill, and more conſtantly follow that which is good. And now we pray thée receiue, vs all this night into thine owne ſafe kéep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: be a good God to euery one of vs. Gard vs in our bodies by the defence of thy holy Angels from all outward dangers and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoeuer: and aboue all, kéepe vs by thy bleſſed ſpirit from euery enticement of
<pb facs="tcp:17263:16"/> Sathan, which might hurt vs in our ſoules. Giue our bodies ſwéete reſt and comfortable ſleepe, and graunt vnto our Soules the ſwéete peace of conſcience, which may prepare vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in whoſe holy name we pray further for all good graces néedefull for the whole Church this of England our Kings Maieſty the Councell, Magiſtrates, Miniſters the comfortles, and all the reſt of the faithfull in any place of the world, ſaying the ſame prayer which himſelfe hath taught vs in his holy Goſpell after this manner.</p>
            <q>O our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>THe grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the loue of God the Father, and the moſt ſweete and comfortable fellowſhip of God the holy Ghoſt be with vs, bleſſe, preſerue, keepe, comfort, and defend eury one of vs heere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, together with all the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Faithfull which in any other place belong vnto Ieſus Chriſt his kingdome, both this night, and for euer heereafter to the end of the world, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer for the Morning.</head>
            <p>WC thy humble ſeruants thanke thee moſt mercifull Father, that thou haſt kept ſo
<pb facs="tcp:17263:17"/> good and carefull a watch ouer euery one of vs this laſt night paſt, that thou haſt ſo merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliuered vs from the darkenes and dangers thereof, and haſt freed vs from euery iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which might not onely haue ſeazed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs in our bodies, but ſwollowed vs vp both in our bodies and ſoules. Our bed wherein we haue taken ſo good reſt and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſleepe, might haue beene our graue to haue ſtopt our breath that we ſhould neuer againe haue ſeene the light of this day if thou hadſt not beene our good God, mercifully to watch ouer vs by thy ſpeciall prouidence. We therefore in the humblenes of our ſoules moſt vnfeinedly thanke thee for this thy defence, and for all the reſt of thy kindnes, either this night, or any time heeretofore. And now we further pray thee that as thou haſt reſkued vs from the dangers of this night, and renued the light of this preſent day: euen ſo it would pleaſe thee to renue the light of thy fauourable and louing countenance toward euery one of vs, in the face and fauour of Ieſus Chriſt, to bleſſe vs with thy ſpirit, whereby we may be guided in all our actions, dealings, and buſines, as thy bleſſed name may be glorified, thy Church and children profited, and our owne conſciences comforted in the aſſured hope of
<pb facs="tcp:17263:17"/> euerlaſting life. Proſper the works of our hands, and make thy feare ſo to proſper in our hearts, that in euery part of our behauiour, we may ſet thée before vs, and make thee iudge, not onely of our outward doings, but of our inward and ſecret thoughts, that the ſame may be vpright in thy preſence, to ſet thée before vs in euery thing we take in hand, calling vpon thee in all our buſines, that thy bleſſing may giue vs good ſucceſſe. Graunt, we beſeech thee, that the words of our mouths, the works of our hands, and all the thoughts of our hearts, may be acceptable vnto thee, both this day and for euer, through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, in whoſe name wee pray further vnto thee for theſe and all other good graces, which thou knoweſt to be moſt needfull for vs and for thy whole Church, ſaying as hee hath taught vs in his bleſſed Goſpell:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>O our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer to be ſtrengthned againſt feare which oppreſſeth the conſcience.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Lord, heauenly Father, I thine vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſeruant, and a poore wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ouerwhelmed with great feare, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my manyfold &amp; grieuous ſinnes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I haue offended thee, my moſt louing and
<pb facs="tcp:17263:18"/> mercifull Father, doe heere bow the knees of my heart vnto thee, beſeeching thee moſt humbly to forgiue all thoſe my ſinnes and heynous trenſgreſſions which make my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſo ſore afrayd, that I neyther can feele ſuch comfort in mine owne ſoule, as may bring peace vnto mine owne conſcience, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther am I able to bee comfortable vnto ſuch as thou haſt humbled by affliction, for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their faith and patience to thy great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and their ſpeciall comfort in the end, though for a time thou ſeemeſt to turne thy louing countenance from them. Good Lord, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my want of zeale, and loue to thee and thy word, I acknowledge my profaneneſſe, and ouer-great looſeneſſe of life, I keepe not back my ſlacknes in hearing, reading, praying, and practizing ſuch duties, as by thy bleſſed word I am bound to performe. Now in the riches of thy mercy worke in my heart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance, for theſe and all the reſt of my ſinnes paſt and preſent: and of thy goodnes, powre ſuch plenty of thy gracious ſpirit into my ſinfull ſoule, that my manners being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and my behauiour both outward and inward being changed, I may both haue comfort in mine owne conſcience, and alſo, without feare, with grace and good courage of
<pb facs="tcp:17263:18"/> heart ſpeake comfortably to ſuch as are in any kinde of diſtreſſe, eſpecially in any trouble of minde, ſo as they may receiue ſome ſpeciall comfort by thoſe gracious words which ſhall proceed from me: Graunt this, moſt mercifull Father, for thy deere Sonnes ſake, Ieſus Chriſt our onely Lord and Sauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A Prayer made at the firſt aſſembly of the Church, when the confeſsion of our faith, and whole orders were there read, and approoued.</head>
            <p>OH Lord God Almighty, and Father moſt mercifull, there is none like thee in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nor in earth, which workeſt all things for the glory of thy Name, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thine elect. Thou diddeſt once make Man ruler ouer all thy creatures, and placed him in the Garden of all pleaſures, but how ſoone (alas) did he in his felicity forget thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Thy people Iſrael alſo in their wealth, did euermore runne affray, abuſing thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold mercies, like as all fleſh continually rageth when it hath gotten liberty and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall proſperity. But ſuch is thy wiſedome, adioyned to thy mercies (deare Father) that thou ſéekeſt all meanes poſſible to bring thy children to the true ſenſe and liuely féeling of
<pb facs="tcp:17263:19"/> thy fatherly fauour. And therefore, when proſperity will not ſerue, then ſendeſt thou aduerſity, graciouſly correctting al thy children whom thou receiueſt into thine houſehold: Wherefore, wee wretched and miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, render vnto thée moſt humble and hearty thankes, that it hath pleaſed thée to call vs home to thy folde, by thy fatherly correction at this preſent, whereas in our proſperity and liberty, we did neglect thy graces offered vnto vs: For the which negligence, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grieuous ſinnnes, whereof wee now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſelues before thee, thou mighteſt moſt iuſtly haue giuen vs vp to reprobate mindes, and induration of our hearts, as thou haſt done other. Oh Lord God, what are wee, vpon whom thou ſhouldeſt ſhew this great mercy? O moſt louing Lord, forgiue vs our vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and all our ſinnes, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake. O heauenly Father, increaſe thine holy Spirit in vs, to teach our hearts to cry, <hi>Abba,</hi> deare Father, to aſſure vs of our eternall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection in Chriſt, to reueale thy will more and more towards vs, to confirme vs ſo in thy trueth, that we may liue and dye therein: and that by the power of the ſame ſpirit, we may boldly giue accompts of our fayth to al men, with humbleneſſe and meekneſſe, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:17263:19"/> they backebite &amp; ſlaunder vs as euil doers, they may be aſhamed, &amp; once ſtop their mouths, ſeeing our good conuerſation. Be merciful good Lord, vnto thy Church vniuerſal, ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad vpon the face of the whole earth: ſend helpe and comfort to al our brethren whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, which are in neede, affliction, or miſery: beate downe the fury and rage of Antichriſt and his Kingdome, and dayly more and more increaſe the number of thy faithful flocke.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed thee in mercy, aboue al other Nations of the earth, to power downe the ſweete ſtreame of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon this little Iland in which we liue, by prouoking of thy Goſpel, and ouerthrowing of Idolatry, wee beſeech thee to continue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſame, and to eſtabliſh in this thy Church a pure perfect, and ſincere regiment thereot, that in the ſame thy glorious Maieſty may be exalted in ſincere, pure, and holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and that this thy Church may flooriſh and increaſe, being through thy ſafe protection ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſupported, &amp; miraculouſly defended, guide and rule, we beſeech thee, with thy holy ſpirit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part and member thereof, eſpecially thy gracious ſeruant, our deare Soueraigne Lord and King, graunt vnto him [O Lord] a pure and perfect zeale, aboue al things, to promote
<pb facs="tcp:17263:20"/> thy glory, giue vnto him the ſpirit of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, diſcreation, and gouernment, that with equity &amp; Iuſtice he may ſee this whole Realme peaceably and quietly gouerned. Deliuer him, O Lord, as hitherto, moſt wonderfully, thou haſt done, from all forrayne and home-bred Traytors, and graunt vnto him (if it bee thy wil) a long and quiet raigne ouer vs, to the benefit of thy Church, and the aduancement of thy glory: bleſſe alſo, we beſeech thee, with abundance of bleſſings, both Spiritual and Temporal, the Queenes Maieſty, the young Prince with the reſt of the King and Queenes Royal Iſſue, and make them worthy Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thy glory, when time and occaſion ſhal ſerue thee vnto: bleſſe, O Lord, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, the Gentry, the Commonalty, and al the Eſtates of this Land: comfort al them that be comfortleſſe, and remoue thy heauy Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from thoſe places on which they are falne: laſtly, for our ſelues we become hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble petitioners vnto thy diuine Maieſty: bleſſe vs [O Lord] with thy grace and peace, make vs thankeful for al thy bleſſings from time to time beſtowed vpon vs, forgiue vs the ſinnes which we haue committed, watch our ſoules, good Lord, and keepe them from all ſinne and vncleanenſſe, from all euil motions and idle
<pb facs="tcp:17263:20"/> fantaſies, and prepare vs more and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the comming of thy Sonne, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And more. O Lord, wee haue commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our ſelues vnto thee, our vnderſtanding is weake, our memory is frayle, and we are not worthy to pray vnto thee, more vnworthy to receiue the things wee pray for; and therefore we commend our ſelues and our prayers vnto thee, in the name and mediation of thy Sonne and Sauiour, humbly begging and crauing both theſe our former petitions, and all things elſe needeful for vs in that forme of prayer which he hath taught vs, ſaying: Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer for true repentance.</head>
            <p>MOſt gracious God. and merciful Father, of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe I haue ſinned and done wickedly, and through thy goodneſſe haue receiued a deſire of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whereunto this thy long ſuffering doth draw my hard heart, I beſeech thee, for thy great mercies ſake, in Chriſt, to worke the ſame repentance in me, and by thy ſpirit, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and grace, ſo to humble, mortifie and feare my conſcience for my ſinnes, to ſaluation, that in thy good time thou mayſt comfort and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mee againe, through Ieſus Chriſt thy
<pb facs="tcp:17263:21"/> dearely beloued Sonne, So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer for the ſtrength and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of faith.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Mercifull God, and deare Father of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt (in whom, as thou art well pleaſed, ſo haſt thou commaunded vs to heare him) for as much as hee often biddeth vs to aſke of thée, and alſo promiſeth that thou wilt heare vs and graunt vs that which in his name wee ſhall aſke of thee: lo, gracious Father, wee are bold to begge of thy mercy, through thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, one ſparkle of true faith and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne perſwaſion of thy goodneſſe and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs in Chriſt, where through, I being aſſured of the pardon of all my ſinnes by the great mercyes of Chriſt thy Sonne, may bee thankefull to thée, loue thée, and ſerue thee in holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe all the dayes of my life, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17263:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
